You can download and illustrate copy of the Gospel story at antiochiant.org slash Christian Education.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
And they will...
praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses
4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
What are we?
permeate everyday life with spiritual presence. Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment
in creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind
throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
evening my giant killers my dragon slayers my stompers on serpents and scorpions
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast, also known as Father Stephen keeps Father
Andrew up past his bedtime.
My co-host Father Stephen Dion is with me from Lafayette Louisiana, and I am Father Andrew
Stephen Damick in Emeas, Pennsylvania.
If you're listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346, just like the voice of Steve just now said.
And Matyska Trudy will take your call, which we're going to get to to the second part of
our show.
Now I know we're live.
We are but are we all the way live?
I don't know there are pre-recorded bits like the voice of Steve for instance, right?
Oh, so so you're saying but you and I are we
Now all the way live are you telegraphing our next episode or do our live amps go to 11?
They do okay, we're a man's a man. Yes, yeah
So Lord of Spirits is brought to you.
by our listeners and also by Chrysostom Academy.
Now I know a lot of you listeners out there,
you work from your homes.
And if you're telecommuting,
you can probably live just about anywhere you like.
So if you're a parent of school age kids
and you're like me,
where you work from a remote or a virtual office,
then one of the big considerations for where you live
is where your kids go to school.
I personally love living in the Lehigh Valley
of Pennsylvania, I've been here for 14 years.
And part of why is because my kids go to Chrysostom Academy,
which is a-
hand orthodox classical school with elementary through high school students.
It's on a beautiful 55 acre campus.
It has the highest economic standards and it's focused not just on educating the mind,
but forming the whole person in Christ.
So if you don't live here yet, think about moving to the Lehigh Valley, sending your kids
to Chrysostom Academy.
And even if you don't tell a commute, our local economy is growing, producing jobs.
You can work at the Peeps factory.
We've got 8 orthodox parishes in our metroid.
area and you can visit croesostomacademy.org to see what I'm talking about. And my wife and I
just went to parent teacher conferences at the Academy this afternoon and we were informed that
all the girls are strong, all the boys are good looking and all the parents are above average.
So I have a question related to your own personal expertise and lived experience.
All right. So you were a stage hand for many years. That's correct. A deck hand.
You now live in the
Ohio Valley. Yes. How many peeps must be consumed in a play before it is officially a peep show?
Wow, I somehow did not see that one coming. I'm just wondering. It crosses that Rubicon.
Tonight. Can I continue? I don't know. Tonight, tonight we wrap up our now 10 parts
series on the sacraments of the Orthodox Church.
Though, of course we could do more.
It doesn't have to be just then.
But we're gonna wrap it up tonight.
And we're also coming to a week earlier
than we normally would because next week
for the Orthodox Church is holy week.
And our following episode is gonna be
on the 27th of April, God willing.
So it's gonna be a few weeks.
This episode though is about the great blessing
of the waters.
Orthodox Christians usually experience this service
at Theophany, which is the Feast of Christ's baptism,
Okay.
also happens as part of the baptismal service.
So what exactly does it do?
It makes holy water, but what is holy water?
Is it magic water?
What is it for?
And does this sacrament have a basis in the scripture?
So obviously though, that means we're gonna start with
blood, right?
Blood?
Yes, yeah.
And you know, you're trying to ruin one of my jokes
because in the script you had blood actually.
What actually which people may not realize is the title of the horror parody of love actually.
And I actually did not know that the signs that Rick Grimes holds up are very different in that one.
Then in love actually. But as you mentioned, this is the conclusion of our sacrament series.
right? We could have sort of punted to the well in the present.
of the Orthodox Church, the whole cosmos is a sacrament.
It's true, right?
So technically everything is, right?
I've seen this, like, 7, 8, 9, 23, I mean, yeah, yeah, and potentially we could list everything.
But we're not going to do that, although tonight we're sort of going to do that.
And that's why we're concluding where we are.
But as you mentioned, we're starting by talking about blood.
A
And if we're going to talk about blood in the Bible, then we got to start with
Not creation. We'll get there later on
But we have to start with
Ables blood which is the first blood that we see the first blood that leaves
Someone's body at least as far as we know
First blood heart wants us
Yes, well first blood was just called first blood
Oh, that's true.
And that it was in Rambo first blood.
Part two. Yeah. And then just Rambo three.
Which makes no sense.
Right. Yeah. But really are we are you looking for a Rambo movie to make?
Actually the first the first one so now you got me on this thing. The first one is actually a very different movie from the rest of the series.
It's been so many years since I've seen any the original first
I believe the story of a traumatized Vietnam veteran.
Yes.
right? Being hassled by the police in this town. Like it's a very different kind of movie. It's
very much a 70's cinema kind of film. And then once you get into two and three, it just turns into like
classic Arnold Schwarzenegger, so Vester Stallone, Sean, yeah.
And damn action movie. Right. Yeah. And then the third one was dedicated originally to the
the brave fighters of the Mujahideen. So there's that. Okay, back to our topic.
Yeah, so it's Able's blood that first gets shed.
And when the blood is mentioned, it's not, right, of course, the actual murder of Able
is not described in some kind of gory detail about what happens with the blood, where the
blood comes in is God speaking to Cain and talking about Able's blood crying out from
the ground.
Right, which there are actually icons of...
this, of this little sort of red man, this little red man crying out from the ground to God.
It was like blood cells or something.
Yeah, it's weird but interesting, definitely.
Yeah.
And so in this case, so in this first case, we're seeing sort of shed blood as symbolic in the larger
of the word of guilt, right, and the looming prospect of vengeance, right, of consequences.
And this gets further developed within Jewish literature, especially once again into the
second temple period, where able become sort of the paradigmatic martyr.
Yeah sure right.
So I know we've mentioned on a previous episode, I think it was when we did the sort of geography
of the underworld that we talked about this, that in 1st Inek, when Inek is being taken
by the archangels on his tour of the cosmos, and they go into Hades, he sees these four
caves in in Hades and the four caves are there to separate
the righteous, the wicked, the ignorant, and the martyrs. And then each of those has a separate
sort of fate coming to them at the at the last judgment. So already in first Enoch Haydes is
sort of this intermediate place. Right. And the way he identifies in his vision, the cave of the
the martyrs as the cave of the martyrs is that he sees one particular
soul, it says, standing outside the cave and crying out toward the heavens. He's told
by the archangel that that is actually able, who is there crying out to God for justice.
He of course is not, even if we're talking in pre-Christian terms, he is not the last
right there's the macabee and martyrs
and in the various texts, mostly second and fourth Maccabees that discuss the Maccabeean martyrs,
those texts are where in the second temple period, sort of the Jewish understanding of
martyrdom sort of becomes fully formed. But this allows, for example, Christ to say
the blood of all the martyrs from able to
So, it was never higher.
It was never higher.
slayed between the ultra-the-high place will come upon this generation.
And everyone knows what he's talking about.
Because there is this understanding of blood that is shed in unrighteousness, in injustice.
This is an injustice where the correct order of things has been thrown off.
and the blood itself, right? The victim...
His existence as victim, his blood which was shed itself cries out to God for the justice to be restored,
which is going to be bad news for the person responsible.
The next sort of important discussion of blood comes after the flood.
Right so this is a ways a ways in the future
but right. Yeah, yeah. But not that far of the text. Right? Yeah. Yeah. Just a
Genesis 4 to Genesis 9. Right? So we're jumping five chapters. Yep. And after
the flood, this is when Noah and his family are given permission to start
eating animals. But it is specified that while they are allowed to eat animals,
they are not allowed to eat the blood of animals.
Yeah, which is interesting.
partly because to me anyways, even though this is not in the Genesis text, a lot of the
other second temple Jewish order that literature that comments on Genesis mentions that the
giants wiped out by the flood are cannibals, right, that they're eating each other and
eating humans and all that kind of thing.
So it's interesting that there's this kind of like, well, okay, it is okay to eat meat,
not blood and although it's not said here, definitely like not people.
Right. Well, that's going to involve the other thing that is mentioned here, obviously,
if you're eating a person. And that's because this is in the same context as the commandment
he who spills man's blood, social, his blood, be spilled by man because man is made in the
image of God. Right? And it even says here that God is going to demand an account for the
blood of every human, even from animals who eat them.
And this is a biblical pattern to notice, right?
Is that when something is sort of being presented in extremists in the Scriptures, you get
animals invoked.
Yeah, right.
Verse five, like from every beast I'll require it and from man.
Yeah.
So you get that here, you get that some other examples of that.
right, the very end of the book of Jonah,
right, in this city, there are these people who don't know
their right hand from their left and many cattle.
And also much cattle.
Yeah, right.
So, right, so this is sort of the taking it,
you know, the inextremist kind of position, right?
But both of these, right, the blood is the life
of the thing.
right? And we've mentioned before on the show that there's this pattern in the early chapters of
Genesis where you go from in paradise eating fruit, which doesn't even kill a plant, right?
Does Doharm even to the plant really long term? Where the creation is sort of offering itself to
humanity for food, to Adam after the expulsion from paradise having to work the ground,
to bring
the fourth food by the sweat of his brow,
sort of having to work and cooperate with it
to produce food.
And so when we get to this point,
where a man is being given permission
within the context of eating to kill animals,
there is still this barrier place to it,
which is designed to prevent man
from becoming completely predatory.
Yeah.
Right.
Humans are not to live as...
editors on the earth, right?
And requiring a person before they eat an animal
to drain the blood, to properly prepare it,
to go through these other processes, prevents that.
So, and there were pagans, who obviously we've talked
before about human sacrifice and related cannibalism,
but there were also various pagan rights.
the DNS
in the series being one example, where they practice homophagy, which is eating animals
alive.
Yikes.
Where they would capture animals and just bite into them while they were still alive.
Like, it killed them while eating them.
Yikes.
So that and that in those rights, right, like in the back at rights, the idea there is
that human
are becoming more animalistic, right?
Giving rain to some kind of predatory impulse.
You know, people talk about those back at crates, basically, it's just being about a bunch
of people getting drunk and then doing embarrassing things.
But apparently it also involves biting into live animals.
Yes.
It was a much darker thing.
It wasn't just a frat party.
Yeah.
I mean, I'd like to say that this is a ruined Sunday school moment, but I'm like, that
would be a weird Sunday school to begin with.
Yeah, if that's what you're talking about.
Oh
But so this is an impediment.
But all of the impediment, everything else is all based
around this idea that the blood is the life of the person,
the animal, yeah.
Right?
And therefore has to be treated in a certain way.
Right.
So what that concretely meant, for example,
You're gonna be an end for good
chunk of human history pretty much all the meat that was consumed by people was
consumed in the context of animal sacrifice. People did not eat a lot of meat.
Yeah, it was not just go down to the local McDonald's or whatever, never big
Mac. Right. And so if you were going to kill an animal for me you almost always
sacrificed it to whatever god you worshipped before you did that. Right. Right.
Um.
And the eating of it was in that ritual context.
So essentially the blood handling for an animal you were going to eat in the Torah is
not fundamentally different practically from the blood handling for an animal sacrifice
because those were the same thing, almost always.
Sure.
Right.
So what do you do with blood?
You go and you pour the blood out at the base of the altar.
and you can report into the ground.
right? That's what Leviticus says to do. Right.
Which, like, what's that, what's that all about? Cause like pouring, like, there's a pagan
practice, right? A pouring blood into the ground and the whole point is to kind of feed
the spirits. We've talked about this, right?
Well, it do a grave. Yeah, into a grave. Right. Right. Right. Yeah. I mean, that's not
What's going on here, right?
Right.
So in
In most, usually when that was done,
with the blood being poured into a grave.
So for example, in Greek temples,
they should pay in Greek temples.
They would typically have the central shrine
to the God or goddess,
and then attached to that would be another shrine,
which was the tomb of what they called a hero,
which is where we get the word hero.
but it was sort of as we've talked about.
about before a different kind of term,
and that this is often a founder figure of a city,
a great leader from the city's past.
Right, this kind of thing.
And the blood from the sacrifices offered to the God or Goddess
would be taken and poured into the grave of the hero.
And the idea there was that, as you see,
dramatize
example in the Odyssey, when Odysseus goes to speak to the shade of Achilles, this is
sort of keeping the shade, the shadowy existence of the person in the netherworld around, right?
Keeping it from fading off into oblivion.
In other pagan rites, the blood was just consumed by priests or participants.
It was sometimes uh...
given as drink to the the God or goddess or spirit
Right that kind of thing so a big part of pouring it into the ground
Specifically at the base of the altar is
It's a way of disposing of it that prevents all those other potential uses. Yeah
Right, and and we still do this in the Orthodox Church, right? This is the way you dispose essentially of sacred liquids
Right.
pouring those into the ground. Yeah, into the ground. Not in any random place, but a set aside
reverential place. Yeah, yeah, where it's not going to be walked on.
So, but this, this image of the blood, the life, right, of a sacrifice being poured out at the base
of the altar, that symbolism that gets picked up later in the scriptures, a good example of this is
in the Book of Revelation the martyrs.
their souls, their lives, right, are beneath the altar in heaven that's ain't John C's.
And they're there crying out for justice, not consistently.
It's the able, yeah, it's the able thing all over again.
Right.
They're crying out how long the Lord will our blood go on a bench, right?
And so this is not the idea here is not that by pouring out the blood.
of the base of the altar, you were feeding the souls of the martyrs. Because, of course,
this wasn't happening in Christian circles by the time the book of Revelation was written.
Right. They weren't like taking the blood of Christ and the Eucharist and pouring it into the ground.
No. Right. So that was no longer a part of this. So that's not in view there. Right.
But it's picking up this martyr idea.
just their location is related to this because of course, say John is wanting to present the martyrs
as people who have offered their deaths as sacrifices to God. Their death was a violent death
right at the hands of violent people. That's what makes the martyrs but they are through their
prayers wanting to transform it into a sacrifice.
on behalf of themselves and their people.
And again, you can read second and fourth macabees
for more of this, right?
Theology of martyrdom, as it grew up.
So the other thing, or a couple other things,
are done with blood though.
So there are a few cases in the rituals of the Torah,
where the blood is not immediately poured out
the base.
of the altar, but is used for something else, which
was not just disposed of, but utilized.
Yeah.
So one of these is when the tabernacle,
and it's accoutral mall, right, the furnishings,
right, the objects that we've talked about
in a previous episode, when they were dedicated,
They were set apart and purified by...
blood by being smeared with animal blood. And so a lot of what's happening here, I won't
jump ahead, right? This seems counterintuitive to us, right? Like, if I got animal blood
all over myself, I would not be like, ah, finally, I am clean and purified. Right.
I'm like, what animal it was?
You mom would say that's never gonna...
come out. Yeah.
That's, um, nor would, you know, if, if when I was a kid, they had told me to, uh,
to clean up my room and I had covered everything, I had splattered animal blood everywhere.
Would they be like, good job? Right. Um,
pretty much. You're very macabre person. Yes.
There will be blood. Yes. I drink your milkshake. Um, so, um,
But something is going on here because this isn't just any blood.
Right? It's not just like, hey, drain me a bunch of animal blood because it makes it good to
detergent. Right? This is sacrificial animal blood.
Yeah.
That's being used for this.
Right?
And it's seen to purify and consecrate and set apart these physical objects.
There!
couple of other instances in which sacrificial blood that is collected rather than being
disposed of at the base of the altar gets put on people.
Yeah, and I mean, this is not all the time.
This is some very specific circumstances.
This is not part of the regular sacrificial pattern.
Right.
One of these only happens once total.
The other one is, well, so the other one is, and we talked about this in our episode on
and ordination was
in the ordination of a priest in the Torah, where sacrificial blood was smeared on the
right-year-low, low-bright thumb and right toe.
And we talked in that episode, you can go back and listen to more about that.
But how that was, sacrificial blood had been used to consecrate the altar.
And so sacrificial blood was being used to create sort of a tether, a connection between
that priest as a human who's been dedicated and the altar, which has been dedicated.
So that happened only when a priest was ordained and began his service.
The other major instance was in the ratification of the covenant and Mount Sinai.
After Moses had come down and...
and read the commandments, the people all said,
oh yeah, we're gonna do all those things.
And they could be not too.
They proceeded not to do any of those things,
but they said yeah, sounds good to us, we're in.
We're gonna do all these things
and then Moses took sacrificial blood
and sprinkled them with it.
So it's kind of a consecration of the nation.
Right.
of them being set apart and having this relationship.
with God, right? Through his covenant, issued it Mount Sinai. Now, as a note, since we're
coming up on Holy Week, and we have some very well-educated folks of the Orthodox Church
who haven't managed to puzzle this out, so we're going to help some folks.
There is this now infamous line in St. Matthew's Gospel.
We've talked before.
on the show about how misunderstood the whole passion narrative in St. Matthew's gospel is
by modern people. Bluntly because they don't know the Torah. Right. Get a read Matthew's people.
Yeah. Yeah. St. Matthew knew the Old Testament. How about that?
St. Matthew. Highly familiar. Yeah. So we had we've talked before about the out of it,
St. Matthew is sort of presenting Christ as both goats in the day of atonement.
And some things related to that, but the very infamous line
Right is when the the crowd shouts out his blood beyond us and on our children
Yeah, which a lot of people take that then to be
This sort of anti-Semitic thing which is number one kind of hilarious because like Matthew's gospel is
I don't know sort of the most Jewish of the gospels well
It's written by a Jewish guy
Yeah, right.
about Jesus who were Jewish.
Sorry.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, I mean, so the idea that the way that people sometimes
read this is like, he's depicting it as we're all guilty
and we'll be guilty forever, you know,
we're the Jesus killers.
To be fair, to be fair in the medieval West and elsewhere,
that text was weaponized in that way.
I guess people in Jewish community.
Yeah, yeah, so this has been read in this way for a long time. Right so Jewish people yeah, right who have those
Associations with it. I don't blame right that it's hard to have distance on that right
Modern educated
Scholars and people who don't get this I have less sympathy for
Right
Because it's pretty obvious
Yes.
Again.
if you know the Torah, what St. Matthew is doing.
St. Matthew is just like with the,
we talked about how he presents Christ being mocked
and spat on and hit with the read,
and how that's exactly how the driving of the goat
out of the city was presented in the epistle of Barnabas,
right, in the day of Atonement ritual.
Yep, yep.
And so the idea there, right, is that
Will these people are just...
hating Jesus, right, and mocking Him and hitting Him and spinning on Him.
But St. Matthew is presenting this as despite what they intended,
despite their evil intent, right, that Christ was serving as the goat and taking away their sins.
Right. And what does the blood of Christ do if it's on you?
It purifies you. It cleanses you.
Right.
Yeah, so what St. Matthew is presenting here?
is that Christ's blood is the blood of the new covenant.
Yeah, it consecrates to this nation.
And while when they shouted that thing, they shouted it out of hatred,
right, that Christ, right,
Christ is the ultimate fulfillment of that whole idea
of a sacrificial death, of a human,
in the preceding Jewish literature and in the scriptures.
Christ turns that
to good, to the good of the people who are doing evil. This is why if you're an
Orthodox Christian and you've been doing the readings you're supposed to be
doing or you went to pre-sangtified liturgy last night, right? You heard the
story of Joseph and Joseph saying when you sold me in slavery in Egypt, you
meant it for evil but God meant it for good and used it to save the lives of his
whole family.
Right. That's why we're reading that now. So that when we hear this stuff in St. Matthew's
gospel, we'll get it. Yeah. Right. And we won't just go online and purchase signal by calling
it anti-Semitic and saying, Oh, tut tut. Right. I'm not referring to anyone in particular.
Right. No, I mean, this cut this, you know, I feel like I see this every year. Yeah. I
Yes, and it's again, read your sub-toy.
Where?
We have a signed reading during Lent.
Yeah.
It's Genesis, Proverbs, right?
Isaiah.
And then there's going into Holy Week.
There's the story of the Exodus, the Book of Job, right?
There's a reason why the church gives us this assigned reading so that when we go to church
and hear the hymns, we'll understand what's going on.
Yeah.
Yep.
Right.
And so.
So we have to take accountability for our own failure to understand, because it's usually
based on us not doing what we were supposed to be doing along the way.
We expect to be able to just walk into a service, hear things, and whatever it seems to be
saying on the face, like, well, that's what it's saying.
And I just react, and I have opinions, and let me voice them online.
Or
Yeah.
Anyway, we'll end that particular rant.
This is becoming a theme with me going after not any particular person on the show.
So,
another important use of blood.
blood and there are several places where this occurs in the Hebrew Bible.
but one of them that's important and recognizable to a lot of folks is the one that's in
Psalm 51 or 50 in the Greek numbering which is usually translated in English,
deliver me from blood guiltiness. Yeah. If you look it up, the Hebrew is literally blood,
It's Domime and...
And so it's literally deliver me from bloods.
Yeah, right.
That's not that's not because the author was a creep.
Um, and you got to that joke fast to the night.
Sorry.
Well, let me get one, man.
Anyway, um, so I'm the one who grew up in Southern California.
I have right.
That's true.
I, I, you know, I read about down the news.
Yeah.
Um, um, so, uh, yeah,
Deliver-
me from bloods and that is an idiomatic phrase, right?
Bloods, blood in the plural, bloods, refers to this idea of like Abel's blood, like the
blood that implies guilt, the blood that's crying out for vengeance.
Being caught red handed as it were.
Yes.
You have blood on your hands.
Yeah.
Right.
course, you know, from the Scottish play where we're letting make
death says out out damned spot.
It's not, you know, it does not mean as I thought,
when I was younger, you know, get the dog out of here
at a time like this, but turns out to be
that she's cleaning blood off of her hands
because she and her husband are murderers.
Oops, boy, they're alert.
Hey, then please, we're not for 400 years.
Some salty language tonight on that.
That's true.
I'm just coding Shakespeare and not even one of the body bits.
So yeah, so and this is
course is not just, oh, I feel really guilty, right? This is in the context of David's repentance.
Right. So David had a murder victim, right, whose blood was potentially crying out to God,
right, preventants. And he's praying and asking God to deliver him from that, to save him from
that because he knows he deserves that, right? Justice should be established. Justice is a good thing.
and justice being established
between him and your eye of the hitite
does not look good for him.
And so he's asking in his repentance
to be delivered from that.
We also see that blood as a substance,
although we've seen how it's used to cleanse
and purify and purge,
it is also treated as unclean
when it gets on things.
And that's even true of sacrificial blood.
And even true of sacrificial blood that's being used to purify things.
So if you are the high priest on the day of atonement, and we're going to touch on,
we've talked a lot about the day of atonement, but you know, blame my dissertation.
On the show, but we're going to touch on that in a minute.
But if you're the high priest doing the day of atonement ritual, which none of us will ever be,
Let me be clear here.
Don't-
Don't try it in your garage.
Don't.
Please don't.
Yes.
I've seen people dressed up to try to do this.
Please don't do that.
Yeah.
So, if you're doing that and you've got this blood and you're using this blood to purify
the objects of the temple to clean them with the blood and some of that blood drips on
your garment.
Your garment is now unclean and has to be burned.
Great, yeah, yeah.
Right, which is not dissimilar to what happens in the administration of the Eucharist,
if the blood of Christ drips on something.
Nope.
So that's...
So blood, even blood that's being used to purify is treated as unclean in any context
outside of that direct ritual application.
in context that are incidental to that ritual application.
So then of course, yes, the day of atonement, as we've talked about before, the day of atonement
is in addition to the regular cycle of daily sin offerings.
This is the annual day of atonement.
It's aimed at purifying the physical sanctuary.
And so those furnishings.
of the tabernacle in the later temple
that were originally dedicated and set apart
through blood, are re-consecrated,
re-dedicated, purified from sort of the residue of sin
by sacrificial blood.
And we have the two goats, right?
The one goat carries the sins away
and then you do the cleanup, right?
of the residue the curse left above.
by sin with the blood, without going way down the rabbit hole, as much as that is my want
in terms of how exactly the blood works to purify the things.
And when I say go down the rabbit hole, right, you could find, if you go and read the literature
on the day of atonement, you will find that there are all kinds of things that the blood
absorbs the residue of the sin, the blood destroys the residue.
of the sin, the blood wipes away, casts a set, right? All different kind of metaphors for
how exactly this worked, but the core idea, as we've said before on the show, is that blood
is life stuff. Sin leaves behind death stuff. Life stuff gets rid of death stuff.
I feel like that could be an advertising campaign. You were talking about a variety of different
cleaners you know.
Yeah, get rid of blood in this spray bottle life stuff exactly in a spray bottle. Yeah. I don't think that would sell well the spray bottle full of like sheet blood, but you know,
You know, you wouldn't do your whole you wouldn't believe some of the I mean you would I think some of the advertising slogans like I was literally driving by
a vacuum repair shop today and
and their advertising line was something like we're going to say
you up for suck, Sess. Like I'm not even kidding. That was the, that was here in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
So if you're driving on Chestnut Street everybody, you'll see what I'm talking about.
Well, if it's related to cleaning fluids, I have to tell the tale of
when I was maybe, oh, I don't know, four or five years old, I think, my older sister and I came
up with a brilliant scheme to make money. We did a lot of that.
brilliant scheme to make money was we need to invent the ultimate cleaning product.
So how do you do that? Well, we got an old mayonnaise jar
and we cleaned it out and we said, well, we want to make the ultimate cleaning product that you
can use to clean anything, right? Like glass, wood, right, cloth, fabric, and everything.
So we got all the cleaning products in my grandma's house and mixed them all together in the
the mayonnaise jar. Which one of you?
first. We did not, because as soon as we had mixed them all, we immediately sealed it with the lid.
So there was this literally black liquid substance. Oh, man. Within this jar. And then we went door
to door in our neighborhood, trying to sell it to someone. Oh, that's glorious.
You never even open up the mayonnaise. Here's the thing I lived in a Dutch neighborhood.
So you can
guess how far that went. Yeah, right. No. We couldn't give it away. So, and I think if you
tried to sell spray bottles of sheep's blood, that's about how far you'd get in most places.
If you did find somebody who wanted to buy it, they probably, someone you should not go
into their house. Yeah. So but where does this all end up then in terms of blood? Right?
in the Old Testament is that as we've seen
going through these different examples,
blood has kind of this ambivalent symbolism,
this ambivalent reality to it, right?
In the real sense of being ambivalent, right?
Two valences.
There on one hand, blood is this purifying stuff.
It's life, right?
And has those ritual uses.
On the other hand, at the
same time blood is extracted from someone or something by killing. Yeah right it
comes from death. So blood is the stuff of life that comes from death. And so when
that comes together what you find and lying behind and connecting all of these
examples we've been working through is this idea that life purification and
transformation emerged from death.
And that within these rituals, blood is the agent by which life, purification and transformation
are brought out of death.
And it's this concept, right, which underlies the Torah, which underlies the Hebrew Scriptures,
that for example, St. Paul is appealing to when he's talking about baptism and death and
resurrection.
right, and how those relate that St. John and first John, we talks about the blood of Christ
purifying us, right? These are all connections being made between Christ and this underlying
reality of the Hebrew Scriptures and the Torah that already was there in talking about blood.
Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, that wraps up the first part tonight, and we'll be back
just a second.
with First Blood Part 2.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
This is Father Stephen Freeman.
I'm happy to announce that
An ounce ancient faiths, publication of my latest book,
face to face knowing God beyond our shame.
Some modern therapists have described shame as the master emotion,
one that colors and shapes our world in ways that we hardly imagine.
The Christian tradition is no stranger to this
and has a rich understanding of the ways this part of our inner life
shapes our experience of the world.
This book out
for something of a road map to that inner life.
What is shame?
Is it always bad?
Does it have any useful purpose for us?
Join me in an exploration of knowing God beyond our shame, finding the true God whom the
scriptures tell us did not turn his face from the spitting and the shame.
to face is now available at store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
Again, it's Lord of Spirits, first blood part two.
actually, um, actually.
We're talking about water in the second half.
Oh, there's not a Rambo movie for that though.
Is there like a Rambo water?
Second water.
No, that's.
Yeah.
Water World, not Rambo.
Water World, incredibly underrated movie.
You think?
Really?
Any movie where people drive jet skis powered by crude oil is a good movie as far as I've
been through.
the stockman movie ever made.
That went in a very different direction than I thought I was going to go.
Also, in relation to the commercial we just heard, uh, I have not yet read Father
Stevens book.
Should I be ashamed of that?
I think he would say so.
But maybe he'll call in and let us know.
I don't know.
Yeah.
Father Steven Freeman, if you're listening right now, give us a ring.
We'll talk to you.
Yes.
Shame me publicly for not having read your book.
Yeah, so, okay, what we've talked about, we talked about blood and now we are going to
talk about water.
So this is, as I said, this is the second part of the show.
Feel free to give us a ring, a five, five, a radio.
Again, let's say five, five, two, three, seven, two, three, four, six, just like the voice
of Steve said.
It's getting to be a lot of Stevens.
You know, Steve, although Steve Christophero actually is not Stephen.
I mean, I think legally his name is Stephen, but his baptismal name is still
us. Still, yeah, no, it's true. It's still, you know, fake Steve. Yeah, it's interesting.
I mean, it's one of the fun things about the Greek American community and Greek Americans,
you guys know what I'm talking about, right? You meet some guy named Steve, you know, his
name is probably actually still in us. Or occasionally if you meet a Stan, it's still
in us. If you meet a Pete, his name is probably not Petros. It's probably Panagiotis. You
Me the Billy, it's, you know, Vasilios.
Y'all know what I'm talking about. So this is this is totally thing. I mean, it's fine. It's great.
It's lovely, you know, but it can be a little a little a lot of a lot of aliases a lot of
a K a's there on the permanent record. Yep. Yep. Spacious. Yep.
So of course, I used like three or four different aliases to join Columbia House Record and Tape Club.
So who am I to talk? That's another good throwback reference. Nice. Yeah.
I can't ever go to-
I've got warrants.
So, yes, Indiana's check.
Check on that for us.
Call the Tarahote Police Department
and see if that's true.
See if it's still after me.
Or Edward Van Sloan, or James D. Steven.
So we are talking about water.
I mean, we didn't start with Genesis 1.
For the last, we started with Genesis 1.
Now we are.
but yeah, now we're hitting Jones.
is one. So it turns out there's water right there at the beginning. Just as one chapter 1 verse 2.
Yeah. So not at the very beginning. Right. We're in verse 2. Right. But
right, we have this image of the spirit of God hovering. It's usually translated over the waters.
as we've mentioned before, the word there that's translated hovering is
actually more like brooding and not the way we normally use it. Right? Like if you're going to
say that Donnie Walberg was the brooding new kid on the block. This is brooding in the original
sense of a mother bird brooding over its eggs. Right. Right. And so this is part of the bird symbolism.
Note, symbolism connected to the Holy Spirit.
The Holy Spirit is not a bird.
You should not draw a bird and say it's the Holy Spirit.
This is bad.
I mean, I can agraphically that sometimes is a thing,
but it's not only at the offening.
Yeah, Holy Spirit is not shaped like a dove.
Yes, it's not a bird.
Don't do it not even once.
But what's being portrayed there by the waters,
right and this is this is
not, I won't directly shout out certain folks, but certain folks who hear this will get it.
This is not talking about H2O, right?
This is not saying there was water like what comes out of my tap before un-created anything.
Right?
but yeah, you're...
you're pushing the wrong liberal buttons.
That's where your brain goes, right?
Sorry, can I have?
So this is, the waters here are primordial chaos.
Okay, so yeah, waters is kind of the best image
that fits this notion.
Right, right.
So this is, you know, primordial case.
us, right? Hoistler is rooting over it before God begins to create. We've talked
before several times about how first three days of creation are putting things in
order and then structuring them with life, right? So but something interesting
becomes apparent when you compare this creation story with creation stories and
and other stories from...
ancient Erystern cultures adjacent to near around previous to Israel.
Yeah, there's some as we like to say, continuities and discontinuities.
Yes, from the Torah. So in the case, for example, of the Bale cycle,
before Bale's escapades, all of which he totally wins,
The
The original Most High God and sort of divine son who presided in the divine council were
King Yam and Prince Nahar.
Yam and Nahar, Yam being the word for C, the C-S-E-A, and Nahar being the word for river.
in the Babylonian creation story.
Right, you've got TMAT who's the great ocean and a dragon and a goddess, right?
And shows up in D&D.
Yes.
Early on.
Yeah.
And then Marduke, not to be confused with Warduke since he brought up D&D.
Marduke and Slayser and humans are created from her blood, interestingly enough.
So what you see here is...
that you see waters representing primordial chaos,
but these primordial chaos is here
an antagonistic force that has to be overcome
by the divine power of a second of a new tier of gods,
in the succession myth.
Right, so you have to do battle.
And this are 19th century German friends,
actually 18th and 19th.
century German friends, coin the term chaos comp, which is what an interesting
transpon-magnification of a word that is. You got to read there,
to read there at the front and then German at the end. Yeah. And because it's, you know,
German in German, you can just take a bunch of words and ram them all together into one big word.
Like, how's Gyshek Teschul? But it's so German. So chaos comp, right, the struggle against chaos.
Right.
the battle against chaos, the war against chaos, right? And this is sort of the genre,
the term that's coined for that genre, often creation stories, sometimes succession myth,
not totally connected to creation, per se. And so it's about this battle between
the new divine and the old divine, which is the forces of chaos and destruction.
When you look at Genesis, you see something fundamentally different.
Right.
Yeah.
Here, the primordial chaos is being brewed it over by the spirit of God.
As if sort of battle.
Yes.
As if the spirit were a mother bird.
And this primordial chaos were an egg.
Huh.
And so while this is chaos
Right? It isn't anything. Right? It's, it's, we talked about this in a previous episode. Right?
That they didn't have the concept of being in nothingness. Right? They had being in chaos. Right?
In the ancient world, including the Greeks. So this is, it's not anything. It's chaos. Right?
But here it's seen as having the potential.
Hmm, right.
It's filled with potential to become anything
Through the power of God
To which it submits when God speaks. Yeah, it's interesting because like in
Even if you think like in Greek myth chaos is sort of like the primordial
divine being
you know that that
out of which other stuff comes like
night and dark.
Yes.
Yeah.
And then even once you get into the Greek philosophers, right, Plato, you've got being
and you've got becoming, right?
With pure becoming, not being anything, but with Aristotle, you've got prime matter,
which is hypothetical and isn't anything, right, but can become anything.
It's pure potency, right?
So this is a recasting.
right of the relationship between God and chaos. This is a very different
presentation and therefore a very different presentation of water already. Now
it should be noted, and I know we've noted this before, that there is chaos
comp language attached to Yahweh in other parts of the Bible. The most well-known
I mean, there's a couple of Psalms, but the most well-known one is probably toward the end of Job
where it talks about Yahweh overcoming Leviathan and pulling him up straining the sea and like with a hook from his nose and
Right fun stuff like that which you know then gets echoed in Norse mythology get Thor and the Midgard serpent
right right now
But the original themes from Genesis also get carried forward in second temple of literature
just one example for folks who may have...
gone to great compliment at some point during this length. Kind of passed that now. But if
you went to great compliment, you heard the prayer of Manasseh, right? It's God's word and
His name that hold back the sea, right, that restrained the forces of chaos once again.
So there's not a struggle. There's not an effort required.
Yeah, I mean, just like Jesus, who can just simply command the winds and the winds.
waves and it doesn't have to go up there and like,
and water.
And water.
For that.
Yeah, it's like Sarman's standing up on his tower
and having to make the weather happen.
You had to get the, you know, you're just feeding
these people, the all one podcast people.
I don't know, that was the image in my mind.
What can I say?
You just kind of shovel and coal into the furnace.
OK.
So next time...
we see water, right?
We jumped from Genesis 4 to Genesis 9 in the first half here.
In the second half, we're going to jump from Genesis 1 to Genesis 6 and 7.
So I mentioned Genesis 6 too much.
People get really excited.
Oh yeah, no, not that part.
Not that part.
Not that part, everybody.
Come down.
So here's the thing.
Here's how we can tell, like on social media or wherever,
how much people actually listen to the show, right?
If they think we only ever talk about giants in the book of Enic, we know they don't actually listen to the show.
That's true.
We do talk about those things, but we talk about a lot of other things.
So the latter parts of Genesis 6 and into Genesis 7.
And that's obviously the flood.
And so the way the flood is presented in Genesis,
Right, again, you get these...
This will...
Some people you get these debates. You know, is this a local flood or a global flood?
Right like is this is this you know and
Those are people thinking in a very scientific materialist way
Because the way the text actually presents what's happening in the flood is that God uncreates the world
Which goes way farther than either of those
Right right right right
What happens in the text of Jesus is God uncreates the world.
So what happens?
Remember on day two of creation, right, God separated the waters above from the waters below.
What happens at the beginning of the flood account in Genesis?
He opens the gateways of the heaven and all the water that was up there comes down.
So that separation gets removed.
Right. And then what?
What did he do on day three?
He separated the dry land from the waters.
What then immediately happens in the flood story.
The fountains of the deeper open and the water comes up and covers the land.
And so in undoing days two and three, God sort of day facto undoes days five and six.
Right.
Which is, you know, the creation of animals and feeling because the world with life.
none of that stuff that used to live in the spaces he created.
on days two and three can now live because those spaces are now gone.
Right? So the life disappears from those spaces. And we're presented with the arc as a literal
microcosm, a microcosmos, right? The creation is preserved within the arc.
And that's it. Right? Through this return to just waters.
And then at the end of the flood,
story, as the waters recede, you see the reverse.
God then recreates the earth.
Yeah, which makes sense because right after the wickedness of the giants is described,
it says that God regrets that he had made man.
So there's this sense of like this didn't turn out the right way.
So let's undo it.
Yeah, yeah, so if you're understanding both the creation story and the flood story and sort of scientific
materialist terms you're missing the whole point. Yeah, that's not to say it didn't happen
Right, it's not the story. It's not the story that's being told in the scriptures. Right. You're approaching it entirely the wrong way
It'd be like saying I mean I'd be like saying you know, so how is that part of you went to?
And instead of seeing the experience that you had and the people that you saw and you
talked to and the way it turned out and how everybody was happy for the birthday boy
or girl, instead you said, well, here's a list of the presents.
And this is what the cake was made out of.
And you know, like, yeah.
Yeah.
Or if the party was boring, you said that party seemed to go on forever.
You were like, no, actually it went on for precisely this length of time.
Right.
How long actually
was the party was longer than an episode of Lord of Spirits.
That would get.
Unless it was one of those crazy frat RPG parties that I hear
they're always yes.
Or a Bacchanalia.
So eventually you ran out of live rats.
That's a callback.
So
But then another sort of place where this flood imagery...
intrudes into the scriptures that a lot of people
either never knew about or forget about aren't aware of is
Actually in the prophecies for example in the early parts of Isaiah about the destruction of Nineveh the capital city of the Assyrians
Because there are all these prophecies that use this water language of water breaking out of destruction of
Right, and...
You know what? You could read them at the one symbolic level of this is saying God is going to remove his restraining hand, right?
Because a Syria has sort of become this force of chaos and destruction in the world.
God is going to remove his restraining hand and they're going to fall prey, right, to chaos and destruction, right?
And this is
the justness of God that's going to that's going to come upon them. But in actuality at 612 BC,
see when Nineveh was
destroyed part of the destruction of Nineveh and the conquest of Nineveh by the neo-Babalone and empire was
destroying the retaining wall and letting the river flood the city. That's part of how they broke the siege
So since I was just talking about literalism
You can see that those prophecies regarding Nineveh were fulfilled both at a kind of quote unquote literal level
level, right, and also at the higher spiritual level, right?
of them falling prey to the chaos of destruction that they had unleashed in the world,
now coming around and settling on them, as another foreign empire comes and destroys them,
the way they had destroyed so many cities and people. So there, in both these cases, the flood,
or the flooding unit, but the water here clearly is this chaos, and it's chaos that is destructive.
Right, that is there to destroy, to kill.
That's the way we're talking about water.
At the same time, of course, you have many episodes in the Hebrew Bible of purification
taking place with water.
Most obvious examples are ritual baths that come to be known as mcphote, which is the plural
of mcpha, which are the places where these are done, but there's the washings of the people,
when they're going to come close to the temple or tabernacle,
of course the washings of the priests before they begin their duties,
washings, hand washings, etc., etc., etc.
Right. All of these things are common washings once you've become unclean
through any number of different ways, ritually unclean,
and then also tied in with being seen moral impurity that's been contracted,
See our baptism episode for some more about.
that, right, clearly the baths, though,
in all of these examples, the washings
in all of these examples, the water involved
in all of these examples, the water here
is not chaos and death and destruction, right?
Water here is purifying.
The water here is removing uncleanness, right?
And so this is a more positive sense and view of water.
And then you have miraculous cures
at that time that in time.
that involve waters. The most prominent one of these, perhaps in the Old Testament is name
in the leper, who goes and dips himself in the Jordan several times and is purified
of his leprosy. In the New Testament, you've got the pool of Bethesda, where the waters
get troubled and someone enters it and is healed. So this is not just a question of
on cleanness. This is...
is also a question of healing.
Yeah.
And it is your purification.
And isn't, I mean, isn't the, we actually
got this question someone said to us
about the pool of Bethesda.
It's called the sheep's pool, right?
Isn't that because it was used for washings
related to sacrificial animals?
Is that right?
So, not to send you up on a big tan.
Yeah.
make you a big
rabbit trail because there's there there are a lot of arguments archeologically about exactly
which pool it was. I see. Okay. Okay. Yeah. So the it was probably the sheep's because
it was by the sheep's gate. Yeah. Into the city. Um, which means that was called that
because that's the one the shepherds used.
Right.
Um, so this could have been a Micva.
for the shepherds when they came in out of the countryside before they went into the temple complex.
There's a lot of possibilities. Possibilities there. But it would not have been to, you could not
put a sheep into a pool to wash it because the sheep would drown. Yeah, right. Right.
Right. Right. So yeah. Okay. All right. So that's a more positive view of water. And of course,
If you're out in the desert...
Right, water and finding water, finding drinkable water is staying alive versus dying.
Right.
So finding a spring of water in the desert represents life, not death chaos or destruction,
right, the exact opposite.
So an obvious example of this is the water that comes from the rock when Israel is wandering
in the wilderness.
Maybe once, maybe twice, maybe the whole time because the rock followed them.
As St. Paul says, referring to a midrashic tradition that the rock followed Israel around in the desert.
There are other incidents in the Old Testament of miraculous springs.
And in particular, the idea of...
of the deserts becoming a fertile place,
a place where water is more available,
gets prophetically associated with the coming
of the Messianic age by prophets like Isaiah.
Right, right, yeah.
So as an example, I mean, there's a few different references
to this, but as an example, in Isaiah chapter 43,
versus 2021.
the Prophet writes, and this is God speaking, behold, I am doing a new thing. Now it springs forth,
do not perceive it. I will make a way in the wilderness and rivers in the desert. The wild beasts
will honor me, the jackals and the ostriches, for I give water in the wilderness, rivers in the
desert to give drink to my chosen people, the people whom I formed for myself that they might
might declare my praise.
Ostriches.
Yeah.
I don't know, just some...
I'm just...
I don't know what he's used so.
I mean, as we've seen before, animals and the Old Testament
can be all kinds of fun stuff.
Yes, yeah, the ostrich worship service.
Right, but so this, right?
This is again, this is not water flooding the desert
as some kind of judgment or destruction.
It is the opposite.
The wilderness, the desert is the place of death and chaos
where people don't live.
where the animals that do live there are unclean animals,
wild beasts like jackals and I guess ostriches, right?
That are out there, right?
And so water, that place becoming watered
by rivers and springs, this is the opposite.
This is life coming to the place of death, right?
This is exactly in the other direction.
And related to that, um...
When the new covenant is discussed, there are several new covenant passages in Jeremiah and Ezekiel,
and Joel in the Old Testament that are pointing to the new or renewed covenant that's going to come
in the Messianic age.
And those are often also associated with water.
And there's one in Ezekiel that is sort of especially pertinent.
in terms of how he says that water is going to be used.
Yeah. Yeah, this is a little long, but worth listening to the whole thing.
You don't have anything better to do. Come on, you're listening to the Lord of Spirits.
That's true. Hey.
So is Ezekiel chapter 26? This is verses 22 through 36.
Therefore, see to the House of Israel
the Lord God. It is not for your sake, O House of Israel, that I am about to act, but
for the sake of my Holy Name, which you have profaned among the nations to which you came.
And I will vindicate the holiness of my great name, which has been profaned among the
nations, and which you have profaned among them. And the nations will know that I am the
Lord declares the Lord God, when through you I vindicate my holiness before their eyes.
I will take you from the nations and gather you from all the countries and bring you into
your own land. I will
sprinkle clean water on you and you shall be clean from all your uncleanness and from all your idols.
I will cleanse you and I will give you a new heart and a new spirit I will put within you and I will
remove the heart of stone from your flesh and give you a heart of flesh and I will put my spirit
within you and cause you to walk in my statutes and to be careful to obey my rules. You shall dwell
in the land that I gave to your fathers and you shall be my people and I will be your God and I
I will deliver you from all your uncle.
cleannesses, and I will summon the grain and make it abundant and leno famine upon you,
and I will make the fruit of the tree and the increase of the field abundant that you
may never again suffer the disgrace of famine among the nations.
Then you will remember your evil ways and your deeds that were not good and you will
loathe yourselves for your niceties and your abominations.
It is not for your sake that I will act to clear the Lord God, but that be known to you.
Be ashamed and confound it for your ways of house of Israel.
says.
the Lord God, on the day that I cleanse you from all your
nicoties, I will cause the cities to be inhabited and the
waste places should be rebuilt. And the land that was
desolate should be tilled instead of being the desolation that
it was in the sight of all who passed by. And they will say,
this land that was desolate has become like the garden of Eden
and the waste and desolate and ruined cities are now
fortified and inhabited. Then the nations that are left all
around you shall know that I am the Lord. I have rebuilt the
ruined places and replanted that which was
I am the Lord, I have spoken, and I will do it."
So a key element of this is that when this new covenant is ratified, rather than
being sprinkled with blood in verse 25, it says he will sprinkle clean water on
them, and that that will cleanse them from all their uncleannesses. But this is a
A new or renewed covenant, right, that still...
involves, right, verse 27, I will put my spirit within you and cause you to walk in my
statutes and be careful to obey my laws. Yeah, right. Repentance. So this still involves
obedience to the covenant. The Holy Spirit is going to empower that, right, after they
have been made part of the covenant by this by water, right, and then being being filled.
with the Spirit. So water here again is both seen in this more positive purifying
cleansing sense and is sort of directly paralleled with blood in the the old
covenant. Yeah, and I thought this was cool here towards the end in verse 35,
whereas there's this reference essentially to the renewal of Eden. This land
that was desolate has become like the garden of Eden.
that this new covenant is in a way the reestablishment of paradise, bringing back to paradise.
Yeah. Yeah. Turning into the place where God dwells. Yeah. And God dwelling there has all these other
effects in the transformation of the world. So obviously, right, if we're going to talk about water,
we've got to talk about baptism, but we already did that earlier in this series and we're not going to
Now, insert the what three plus hours we did on baptism before.
But here that was.
So we will refer you back to that episode.
The, and now, and now, in a break with tradition,
have we lost our minds here at Lord of Spirits?
We are going to talk about the great blessing of the waters,
the sacrament, the mystery of the great blessing of the waters
in the second half.
Does that mean there's no third half to this there is a third half? Oh, okay
There's a route of fear nonetheless
It's originally I was gonna refer you back to our Theophanie episode
But we haven't done a Theophanie we have not done a Theophanie episode. It's kind of shocking actually
I
Then thought well, I could still refer the back to the Theophanie episode that would be in character, but I said no
Our listeners deserve better than them.
that. There's still smarting from the last time we referred back at things that never happened.
That never happened. Yeah. Every so often somebody pops up and is like, wait, what?
So theophany, of course, January 6th, feast of Christ's baptism.
Right. And this obviously relates to what this is.
is the primary place where we do the great blessing of the waters.
Yep.
In a couple of versions, usually one in the church, we also do, there's an outdoor version
where we would go bless a body of water, like Lake River, in my case a duck pond.
Nice.
You don't do the bayou?
Well, I don't want an alligator to eat the cross.
We'll put it that way.
That's an important practical consideration.
Yes.
legit here
the history or the young men who dive after it. Yes.
So, but the offening, right, we're talking about Christ's baptism.
And the chapter of baptism, episode, all those things,
most of those things are things Christ didn't need. Right? Christ didn't need any sins remitted.
because race was without sin.
Right.
Yeah.
Christ did not need purification because he was pure and holy.
Right, right.
Yeah, I mean, the whole deal is that when Jesus touches something unclean, namely the creation
having been polluted by sin, that he cleans it.
Yes, yes.
And this is an overarching theme, right?
So in the Torah, if you go and touch someone with leprosy, you are now unclean.
Well because you may
have contracted leprosy. And so you have to be treated as unclean until you can be verified
that you did not. When Christ touches someone with leprosy, they are cured of leprosy.
So this is overarching, but of course, in the case of baptism, Christ purifies the waters
by his descent into them. And remember why him purifying water is
important is to post to purifying trees or purifying other things he touched. Right?
Waters are so important because waters, the waters are a primordial chaos.
Right. This death-cast destruction imagery that Christ purifies the waters from that.
And this is why in the theophony icon, if you look down in the corner, you'll see.
see little Yam and Nahar hanging out there.
Yeah, the little guys that are on, you know, sometimes it looks like one of them is writing
on a fish.
Sometimes there's some other kind of sea beast.
Sometimes they look like the people and the family and the sea monkeys had.
Oh man, that's another great callback.
Yeah.
You know, my cousin got sea monkeys one time.
I never thought they were real, but she actually got them.
Yeah, I mean, and I often these figures, if you're looking at an icon that's in Greek,
for instance, they'll be labeled, sometimes the figures are labeled, sometimes they're
not.
But if they are labeled, often you'll see them labeled as Thalessa, which is the seas,
the sea or the ocean, and then Yoradhani, the Jordan in particular.
Or Potomose River.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's basically the right that the C and the rivers but you know, it's
Yaman the Harf. They're down there. And Jesus is, he's stomping on them by virtue of being
baptized. Yeah. And stomping on snakes, right? And sometimes directly, right? Crushing the
heads of the dragons that lurked there as it says in the prayers. And so this is, this is
the idea of Christ-pureifying creation.
So originally, right, we now...
And by now, I mean, you know, the last 16 centuries,
like in an era where we have separate feasts of Christ's
nativity, his circumcision in the flesh and theophany, right?
The baptism.
The 12 days of Christmas, inclusive, right?
before about the year 400 in the East.
Now we know.
know that with some precision because we actually have the homilies that St. John
Crosostum preached on the first two celebrations of nativity and
constant noble. Before that, and you can see this for example if you read St.
Gregory the theologians oration number 38, the only the only feast of Christ
because the feast of St. Stephen was already being celebrated to on the 27th.
but the only feast of Christ that was
celebrated in that winter period was the offene was January 6 was the baptism
and that was nonetheless treated as as you could see from what Thick Gregory
says the feast of the incarnation. Yeah kind of all that stuff together I mean in
the Armenian Church they still do that it's still all of January 6 which is
not related to everybody to January 7th, which is old calendar Christmas.
It's not the same thing.
No, all Orthodox Christians celebrate the Nativity of Christ on December 25th.
We just disagree about when that is.
Yeah.
It's different.
On number 25th.
So, right, but so the reason the way that works, theologically, is that this Christ blessing
the waters by descending into them is also taken to be paradigmatic of the incarnation.
We're going to see if we can...
really apparent you read that aeration of St. Gregory I mentioned you read St. Athanasius on
the incarnation that Christ in the incarnation. God the second person of the Holy Trinity,
right? The Divine Logos, right? By being incarnate touches all of our humanity.
and thereby purifies it, our humanity, our human nature, and unites it to God.
That is what the incarnation does for the fathers.
And so his purification of the waters by descending into them is emblematic of his descent
in the incarnation.
Yeah.
And that's what ties those two ideas together.
And this is why from the 4th century onwards, the Church has said that for example, Apollinarians,
say that Christ in
not have a human soul.
Have been said by the church, you not be Christians.
Yeah, yeah, because Christ didn't have a human soul,
he didn't purify our soul.
My soul is it's purifying.
So I'm in trouble.
Yeah, I mean, is it St. Gregory, the theologian,
who has that famous saying,
you know, whatever is not assumed is not healed,
meaning whatever, if there's some element of human nature
Jesus that the Son of God is not assuming.
to him his person, then it's not saved.
It can't be healed.
Yes.
Yeah.
So I'm sorry, William Lane Craig.
The entire Christian church of the fourth century
would like to have words with you.
Indeed.
But if you're listening, William Lane Craig,
please give us a call.
We would love to discuss this with you.
Yes, we will discuss any point with you
because you are frackedally wrong.
You are wrong on every point of doctrine.
Every single one.
And if the topic you are just...
as wrong as your whole system is. So please call us and discuss it. He's not even in the
friend of the show category. This is no. No. No. No. These are the fructively wrong category.
It's rare that I call someone out by name. Wow. There's, but this is the guy who deserves it.
There's hope for you though, Dr. Craig. There is hope. Yes. Repent.
So give a story.
Becoming a Christian.
Okay.
That wasn't harsh.
Give it the situation.
So, right, this is fundamental to house salvation works
in Christianity.
So, another example of this that we,
from the Old Testament, that we read
and that we read at theophany,
that we read in the context.
of the great blessing of the waters is of course the story of the waters of
Mara, Mara meaning bitter. There's the bitter water the wood is thrown into it by
Moses and it becomes drinkable. Yeah right the purification of the waters the
wood they're taking to be symbolic of the cross and therefore of Christ.
So but interestingly or maybe maybe less interesting maybe you're already
tipped off to this.
because of our discussion of Yaman Nahar and that the
off-and-e-i-con.
But in the prayers that we pray at the great blessing of water,
there is this peculiar mention of bail.
Yeah, how about that?
And I mean, I should say everybody,
like if you have not been present at the great blessing
of water, go.
These are some of the most awesome prayers ever.
I mean, really, really stunning stuff.
So yeah, okay, so here's this one.
little excerpt from what is a quite fulsome sort of prayers for the great blessing of water. We did not say it's the medium or small blessing of water.
It's the great blessing of water. So, okay. So here's the bit.
For thou art our God who, through water and the Spirit, has renewed our nature, grown old through sin.
Thou art our God who, with water, distrawn sin in the days of Noah.
Thou art our God who by the sea through Moses, did set free from slavery to Pharaoh the Hebrew
race. Thou art our God who dis cleave the rock in the wilderness so that water gushed
forth and streams overflowed and it's satisfied that thirsty people. Thou art our God who
by water and fire through Elias, dispring Israel back from the deception of bail. It's
one of my favorite passages actually in those prayers.
And so I know there are people who think that this stuff with the profit of live just
analyze.
Sun Mount Carmel gets thrown in there just because they dumped a water over the sacrifices
before the lightning, sorry folks, the lightning comes down and fries it and you know blasts
through the water.
That's not the only reason why.
Right.
And we already talked about this Yamuna Har.
God in defeating Bale shows that it is here.
Who deals with, specifically Christ, right?
Who deals with primordial chaos, death destruction.
Yeah.
The power's thereof.
Well, and I mean, not bail.
As we set up from Ezekiel 26, there's this idea of sprinkling that clean water and
it notices cleansing from idols, from your idols.
like this, there's this connection of, again, you know,
We're brought back from the deception of bail in this prayer that there's this cleansing
with the water also cures idolatry.
Yes, yeah.
And that deception being that bail is the one who does this or can do this.
That he thinks he's something but he turns out he's going to lie he tells you.
Yeah.
Right.
Yes.
God's Venetian are worthless.
So, right, this is the service of the great blessing of the waters, right?
This is the sacrament, the mystery of the great blessing of the waters, right?
This produces holy water, right?
So you go home with your little bottle of holy water, right?
After the service.
This is, as we've said before, on the show, not magic water for killing vampires with.
It is not a material component for your fifth and
six level cleric spells. This is water that has itself been purified to be something which
brings purification and life, and that is then used for blessing other people, places,
and things. Right. And while holy water is used, right, we've got the... I've got a copy
here at least in my
office of the great book of needs, right, which is all the ways to bless all kinds of things.
Right, so you go through an alphabetical order, right, you need to bless an apiary. Here we go,
here's the prayers. Right, true. Like all these vehicles, vehicles, right, flocks,
I'll guide the things, right?
A influences the most common thing, right, that you see, right?
in regular sort of Orthodox parish life is that after the offening, following the
offening and the great blessing of the waters, that water is taken by the
priest who comes to bless the homes right of the faithful. Right. And you come
and priests will come. There are prayers and holy water is sprinkled throughout
the house to sort of re-dedicate it. Right as I'm sure I've said before on the
show, I tell folks that I only have to come do
every year if you sin in the house during that year. So if you go a year without sinning, I don't have to come back.
Not a lot of folks have pulled that off yet. Yeah, I mean people say, look you don't have to come father, but fine, you know.
I guess that means you're saying you have not or no one has sinned in your house in the last year.
Yeah. But every once in a while, every so often, this usually happens when I have a person in our in our parish family
in our parish family.
who has a spouse or someone else in the household who is not an Orthodox Christian.
And they are some other sort of Christian and you come into the house and you do the house blessing.
And they kind of say what's up with that? And usually what's up with that? Uwe, what's up with that?
that takes the form of, where's that in the Bible?
Yeah. Well believe it or not. That's in the Bible. It is. It's in that book that I don't
know. A lot of people are not super into Leviticus, but if there's one thing that we accomplish
through the Lord's Spirit's podcast is to get people to read Leviticus, I think it will
have all been worth it. Turning people on to Leviticus. It's true. It's true. So Leviticus
chapter 14 starting with verse 49 and going through 53.
and for the cleansing of the house.
He shall take two small birds with cedar wood
and scarlet yarn and hisop,
and she'll kill one of the birds
in an earthenware vessel over fresh water,
and she'll take the cedar wood and the hisop
and the scarlet yarn along with a live bird
and dip them in the blood of the bird
that was killed and in the fresh water
and sprinkle the house seven times.
Thus he shall cleanse the house
with the blood of the bird and with the fresh water
and with a live bird and with a...
would and his up and scarlet yarn and he shall let the live bird go out of the
city into the open country so he shall make a tonement for the house and it
shall be clean. Yeah bird blood I mean yeah yeah so thankfully thankfully and just
for the record in case you know you're a catacumin or something or a
inquirer and you've never had your house bless we no longer use the bird blood
it's just the water and yeah if you look
And if you look at the larger context of this, right, this is the, this is one of the things
Father Stephen loves to mention over and over again is that there's laws for how you, how
you do with mildew in your house.
Yeah.
This is part of the context.
But the idea is that the house is impure.
It's described as unclean by the text and this is how you get it clean.
Right.
And notice, notice what this is structured after.
This is the Day of Atomit Ritual in Microkosm.
At a smaller level, right?
It's not for God's house, it's for your house.
So we don't have two goats, right?
We have two birds.
Yeah.
And if you read the rest of Leviticus, you'll see how that relates, right?
The offerings, right?
Birds is opposed to a lamb as opposed to a ram as opposed to a bull, right?
We have two birds.
One bird is killed and its blood is mixed with the water that's used to purify the house,
the other bird is let go.
And where is it let go?
Outside of the city into the open country.
And this is to make a tonement for the house.
So even though this comes in the context, as Father Andrew said,
of cleansing from and your your translations will differ.
Mildu, leprosy, right?
And this is leprosy of a house.
So the word that's translated leprosy,
the Old Testament covers not only skin disorders
but all kinds of things, disease.
However we want to take it, right?
We have the word in verse 53,
a tone make atonement for the house.
Yeah, which is interesting.
Which is the physical house again.
You make atonement for objects.
Yeah, even though the house didn't send.
But yeah, it's been defiled.
Yes.
Yeah.
So this is the same pattern.
So this is dealing with, it's in kind of where this dealing
was sent, too.
Right.
Remember, and we talked about in the unshewess episode,
this connection between sin and sickness, right?
And mildew is seen as a sickness of the house, right?
And how exactly that connection works.
So house blessings in Leviticus, right?
now we just
cut out the animal blood and just use the water. So as we come now to the end of
the second half, we find with water in the scriptures sort of the same thing
we found with blood, right? That water is ambivalent. On one hand water is the
stuff of life. If you're in the desert, right? You need to drink water to live. You
the source of fresh water.
Water is also used for purification and cleansing, right?
But water also symbolizes the forces of chaos
and death and destruction.
Yeah.
And so what do you find?
You find the same kind of paradigm as we saw with blood.
With water, you have chaos, destruction, death,
transformed into life and purification by Christ.
with water just as we
saw with blood. Yeah parallel. Yeah cool. All right. Well, that is the end of the
second half of this episode of Lord of Spirits. And we'll be right back with the
third part. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a
moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a
call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Jesus' last words to his disciples were go and make disciples of all the nations.
Unfortunately many parishes are struggling to follow this commandment.
In reclaiming the Great Commission, Father Evan Armitas offers a road map to help us get
back on track.
Relying on his 20 years of parish experience, holy scripture, and insights from research
and his visits with churches across the U.S., he discusses how you and your community
can implement changes that will train.
form, revitalize and renew your parish. You'll learn how to diagnose and remove the barriers you face.
Deal with resistance to change. Define what a healthy parish looks like. Lead with purpose and
create a parish health plan. Written for clergy, council members, ministry leaders, small groups,
and all committed parishioners. This book will help any church in its journey to reclaim the great
Commission. Purchase it today at store.AncientBate.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
I was trying to come up with a Rambo 3 joke, but it was just when coming to me and then
I started going through Highlander jokes in my head and it got really ugly.
Yeah, it will I mean
Yeah, we definitely don't want to dedicate the third half to the brave fighters of the
Mujahideen.
New that would be a very bad thing to do.
That didn't you're not doing that.
That didn't go very well.
Yeah, I wasn't planning for Rambo references.
I don't know.
Yeah, well, I mean, the place to take this I would think would be the parity of
of the opening scene of Rambo 3.
in Hot Shot's part, do.
Oh, wow.
Which I saw, but don't remember much of where.
Rather than dipping his wrapped hands in broken glass as Rambo, Charlie Sheen dips them
in a series of TCBY yogurt condiments.
You know, gummy bears, M&Ms, at all.
Yeah.
you
Crumbled up nuts.
Strawberry sauce.
Anyway,
you brought up Rambo.
This is all you're fine.
It's fine.
I was I was also trying to
find everything.
Like I was trying to make a
demolition man.
That's that's an under
appreciated movie.
Demolition man is
prophetic.
Yes.
It all lives is the world
for seen by demolition man.
Where is our Dennis Leary to
save us?
I ask you.
He's playing an Irish cop in every movie in TV show.
Oh, that was rhetorical.
Okay, everyone.
That's true.
Yeah, yeah.
Melo Greene's, Warden Williams-Brothers.
If you had wanted to go for a deep cut,
you could have gone for the Rambo Cartoon.
Oh, man, I never saw that, but I do remember its existence.
Oh, it was pure genius, because I mean,
what says children's cartoon in the late 80s
more than a hard R.
action movie. Right. Right. Right. So you take John Rambo and like he can't have any guns or
shoot anybody because it's a kids cartoon in the late 80s. Sometimes when you tell people about
the 80s they're like, no, that can't be right. No, no, I was there. So he's got like a survival knife.
But of course he's not going to stab anybody. It's a children's cartoon in the late 80s. So much
like he man sword he uses it like as a grappling hook
I know, and like a tool.
Whew.
So, you know, the people that don't like our digressions
are just really hating this third half so far.
Well, it's okay.
You pay your money and you take your chances.
That's right, that's right.
So yeah, first part was blood, second part water,
and now creatively blood and water.
Yes, see what we blood and water.
So yes, so
And where where we're taking this you may already have an idea from where the last two
have each ended but as we begin this third half I want to kind of focus on one of the prayers
that we and by we I mean priests have been saying in Great Lent thus far.
And this is related to, so I know we have listeners who...
aren't orthodox or who are inquires or catacumans and maybe don't know the ends out of this. So,
I'll explain slightly what we're talking about.
And a lot of orthodox probably don't know about this either because it's done quietly and you
don't really see it unless you're in the altar. Yeah. Yeah. So one of the canons of the council of
Nice. Yeah right says that on weekdays during lint you are not
consecrate the Eucharist. The West left off following this a long, long time ago.
Yes, sure. But not as long as some people might think, but a long time ago.
So what that means functionally is you so you're allowed to have a regular
liturgy where you celebrate the Eucharist on the Sabbath, Saturday, and on the Lord's
Day Sunday.
during Lent, but not Monday through Friday. Right. Because it's so such a penitential period.
And the divine liturgy is regarded as Festl. And so that's considered fundamentally incompatible.
Yeah. Right. Nevertheless, the people wanted to receive the body and blood of Christ to receive
the Eucharist during the week.
So services were crafted.
There are actually more than one.
But the one that has stuck that Orthodox Church is still used is the pre-scientified liturgy
which was composed by St. Gregory the Deologist, aka St. Gregory the Great, the Bishop of Rome
at the end of the 6th century.
So ironically this is a service written by a Pope that we use in Roman Calixto.
So the pre-sangtified liturgy is a service for giving the Eucharist to the people, but
not actually celebrating it and consecrating it.
Yeah, it's basically Vespers with the reception of Holy Communion at the end.
Right.
the main parts of the liturgy, all the prayers are sort of gutted out of it because you're not.
right? Yeah. And so the portion of the bread that is given to the church that is used for the
Eucharist is referred to as the Lamb, right? That becomes the body of Christ. And so the way this
works is if you're going to be doing pre-sanctified liturgies during the week, you consecrate extra
lambs on at the uh...
Lord's Day Sunday, Divine Liturgy.
So, if you're going to be having two pre-saintified liturgies during the coming week, you would
consecrate three lambs on Sunday morning.
One would be given as communion then.
The other two, you would save in a box called a Picks, which means box.
Or Artofurion, which means the thing that holds bread.
Yes.
And you save that until the service during the week and part of the service is
removing it from its storage place and preparing it to be given right to the people. And so
those lambs which are going to be saved from the Sunday into the week to be
distributed at the pre-sanctified liturgies.
There are a couple of prayers that are said at the time that you are
preparing them at the Sunday morning divine liturgy, which involves some of the blood of
Christ being taken from the chalice and administered to combined with the body, the extra lamb.
Yeah, and there's a couple of different ways I've seen this done. I think the rubric that we have
explicitly says to use the spoon and then to
dip it in the chalice and then turn the lamb upside down and place it in sort of a cross-shape on the
bottom. If I remember correctly, I don't have the book in front of me. But I've also seen some people
just simply take the whole lamb, some priest, I should say, take the whole lamb and just sort of dip it
a little bit into the chalice. Either way, the result is the same, that there's now the blood of
Christ is now combined with the body of Christ in this Lamb.
and then it gets put into the box and set aside.
And so all of this explanation was leading up to us,
us reading you the first of the prayers you said
that the priest says while he does this,
while he combines the body and blood for the lamb
that's being saved for during the week,
the pre-sacrified life.
Yeah, so this is cool.
Yeah, this is just the first of two
and they're both pretty short
because the whole thing only takes a moment
to actually get done.
But yeah, so here's the first one.
With the emptying of the divine blood
from theine undefiled and life giving side,
O Master Christ, sacrifice to idols,
hath ceased and all the earth
does bring unto thee the sacrifice of praise.
That's interesting, because it's got a whole bunch
of these themes we've just been talking about
all right there, and that's for little prayer.
Right, right.
And there's a connection being made here
Between the blue
blood and water that flow from Christ's side at the crucifixion,
and deliverance from sacrifice to idols.
Yeah.
Which is not necessarily on its face
and intuitive connection.
Right, right.
If you've listened to the rest of this episode,
you've already gotten some of the building blocks
for how to understand this, right?
but that's not immediately, that's not no-
Normally, if we're working our way through St. John's Gospel and his account of the crucifixion,
at that point, you usually don't get into a lot of discussion of sacrifices to idols.
The things that are usually drawn out there, and if you read the church fathers on that passage,
have the opening of a side being compared to. And this is...
The passion narrative in St. John's Gospel is full of language.
I know we've mentioned this on the show before from Genesis.
But the opening of the side, in the opening of Adam's side, to produce his bride, Christ's
bride being the church, the blood and water, baptism and the Eucharist.
That's kind of the connections that are usually drawn out there.
What's going on in this prayer with Sacrifice to Idols?
Right? Being what's delivered from. Right? So we have to make sort of a distinction here,
right, in terms of, and we're picking up the threads that we left at the end of the first two
halves, which talked about this ambivalent nature of both blood and water, and a sort of
transformation or redemption of blood and water.
Right, how they go...
from chaos, death, destruction to life, purification, right?
To really zoom in on that, right?
So blood and water as material things, right?
H2O and whatever the chemical composition of blood is.
Be much longer, not a biochemist, right?
But, right, them as material don't need to be redeemed, don't need to be saved, right?
Because, right, contra-nosticism, material things are not innately evil, bad, fallen,
whatever, right?
Yeah.
I mean, God created it, saw that it was good, right.
And, you know, the other part of the symbolism, the other thing that's drawn together there,
right?
Chaos, death, destruction.
things can't be redeemed. What do I mean by that? Not that they can't be turned to good,
but that, right, in the new heavens and the new earth, there's not going to be like, it's not that
now death is going to be good. It's that there's not going to be death. It's not going to be good.
It's that there's not going to be chaos. It's not that now destruction is going to be good. It's
going to be there's not going to be destruction. Right. Right. It's like, you know, sickness. It's
It's gonna be that good kind, you know?
Yeah, yeah, it's a good kind of, yeah.
plague. Right. So those, the other side of it can't be redeemed. Right. But that relationship
between them is not just symbolic, meaning two things brought together. That's not that
bringing together is not just something that happens in speech or thought or analysis
or idiomatic language.
Right, that's not the only connection. It's not an arbitrary connection of language that might be connected totally differently in terms of symbolism and a different culture.
And it's not just something the Bible is doing, right? This is the biblical symbolism of this.
But this is a connection in reality that's being pointed to, but it's a connection in spiritual reality.
that there is a connection between
the material things and the spiritual forces, the spiritual beings,
the spiritual powers, the spirits of death, chaos and destruction.
Yeah, so there's essentially an exorcism that needs to happen.
Right, right.
And we can see this, right there, so there are a couple of texts in first John
that make this really pull
So first John 5 verse 19 says that the whole world lies under the power of the evil one.
And that word lies there.
Whole world lies under, right?
Is not just a statement of sort of geographical location.
Yeah, right.
Like power the evil one is on top.
It's below it.
It lies.
Lies five miles to the west.
Yeah.
That word that's translated lies really is like laying down like prone like supine, right?
That this is this is an an image of helplessness
Yeah, like like the evil one has pinned the world. Yeah, it's pinned it to the mat
more than a three count right
and
and that it's been sort of...
It has this imagery of overpowering and oppression.
Right?
And when it says the whole world here,
if you read the preceding verses in 1 John, right,
this isn't the whole world like,
oh, the cosmos, the creation in an abstract sense.
This is very much St. John distinguishes
the things in the world.
Hmm.
He's talking about objects.
animals and plants and people in the world now lie in this powerless state
under the power of the evil one. Right. The second passage in first John is
first John 3 verse 8 which says as you might be reminded if Jamaican Johova's
witnesses show up at your door that
Christ, it came to destroy the works of the devil.
Right? To destroy the works of the devil. That's not talking about people who are the works of the devil.
No, it's that's not talking about things the devil created because the devil can't create anything.
Yeah, it's his works, which humans do. Right. By humans doing the works of the devil, they have subjected
The creation through sin and the curse that sin
they have subjected themselves the things in the world to the power of the devil.
And Christ has come to destroy the works of the devil, to break that link,
to break that connection forged by sin and curse, between the devil and the material things of the world.
And, lest we forget what we said in our unsuitable episode that confused some people.
We're coming back to it. Our next episode, the week after bright week.
We're going to talk about the soul, but lest we forget you are your body, so you are a thing in the
material world. Yeah, you're not just a... You're not just... You're not trapped in the material world.
And even if you're a material girl.
It is 80s night on Lord Jesus.
So, you are your body, right?
Again, contra-nosticism, right?
It is not that your body is something in the material world,
which is evil, and therefore your body is evil,
but your soul is good, and you have to escape.
This is you are your body, you are a thing in the world.
Right, and each one of us through our complicity in
sin through the devil has brought ourselves under cursed and has placed our self under slavery
to sin, right? And the powers of the powers of evil. So nothing in the world is innately evil.
Yeah. I mean, again, Genesis, right? One and two. But it is under the curse. It has been subjected
to the curse by humans, by human evil.
The fact that no thing in the world is an ately evil includes humans.
No human is an ately evil.
But humans are enslaved by sin.
They're not totally depraved?
No, sorry, Calvinus.
Not only are all humans not an ately evil, no human is an ately evil.
So human was created by God to be evil.
and to be damned. Second council of orange. Sorry again, Calv.
Right. Every human being in so far as they exist, right. It exists in the world is a good thing
created by God, right. But they have become enslaved to sin. They've come under the curse of the law.
Right. Deuteronomy 30.
They're saying they've come under the power of
the powers of evil in the world
through sin.
And the fact that it's not just that all people are not, right, or that there's no group of people that is.
But there's no particular person is.
So the worst person in the world, the worst person you can think of, the most horrible person you can think of.
Which should actually probably be yourself, but for most of us is not.
We can usually come up with a...
people more horrible than ourselves. Right? That person is not innately evil.
That person is enslaved to sin and death and the devil through what they've done, the choices
they've made in their life. Right? But that does not make them evil. Yep. Yep. Right. There's no such
much thing as an evil person.
But there are people who are thoroughly in the thrall of evil powers.
Yeah, right.
They're slaves.
Such that they're doing the works of those evil powers continuously.
So what this means is, and trigger warning for the word I'm about to use, but I don't
care.
that evangelism is liberation.
Clearly by that I mean I'm a communist. No.
The...
Right.
So we're getting ready to celebrate Holy Week next year.
Or next year, next week.
And also...
And next year too.
Got to be...
Yeah.
Got to be.
But next week we're celebrating Holy Week.
Holy Week is the lead up to and culminates in PASCA.
which is just the Greek word for Passover.
That's right.
Yep.
Right? So we're getting ready to celebrate Passover.
What is Passover all about?
Released.
Read Exodus as you're supposed to next week.
Yeah.
Released from slavery to Egypt.
Manumission, right?
The freedom, freeing of slaves from bondage to,
in the case of the Passover, very explicitly
in the book of Exodus, the gods of Egypt.
Yep. Yep.
Right.
And so the power of the gospel, the power of the story of Christ's defeat of death, of chaos,
of destruction, of the powers of death, of the evil powers of sin. The power of that is to set you
free from it. And anyone can be set free from it by that. Remember, as we mentioned in the episode
on St. Constantine the Great, St. Paul's goal was to get to the Roman Emperor and preach the Gospel to him
and bring him to salvation in Christ. And for a good chunk of his ministry, that Emperor was
Caligula. One of the worst ever. St. Paul thought that Caligula could be saved.
Say, Paul thought Caligula could repent.
Hmm.
Luffy.
just heard the gospel of Christ.
He could, right?
Because why?
Because Caligula, as a human, was not innately evil,
but he was thoroughly in the thrall of the gods of Rome.
And the death and destruction, they were at chaos,
they were wreaking through him.
But he could be saved from that, right?
He could be pride loose from that by the gospel.
So if we understand this,
If we understand this as liberal.
as freedom from slavery, right?
Then we need to understand obviously you can't free someone
from slavery by force or compulsion against their will.
Yeah.
Why?
Because they'll just go back.
Right, right.
Right.
Conversion by the sword or, you know, sorry, Spanish acquisition, which no one expected.
But the
the Levonian Inquisition, I don't know, those are crusaders.
But still, crusaders, trying to convert people with a sword,
not a good scene, not a good, right.
And this is so,
this is so much a reality that we even see
before Christ heals the paralytic
by the pool of Bethesda that we already mentioned, right?
Do you want to be healed?
And that, that sounds like an absurd question.
Yeah, right, but like...
I mean, think about it.
I, as a Christian, know all the things that I need to do to be healed, right?
Or even just as a human being knowing things about, you know, my own health, my own material
health.
I know the things that I could be doing, but I don't do a lot.
And, you know, I don't do them.
So do I actually want to be healed?
Do I want to be healthy?
Do I want to be saved?
you know
On some I mean God willing on some level the answer is yes, but also on a big level the answer is
No, I don't I don't want to be healed so it's actually not that weird of a question because yeah rock and I'm doing it and
And people can find a kind of happiness in slavery
Yeah, right. It's just easier. It's Jeff. If you're a paralyzed man
Who makes his living by begging and you get healed?
Nobody's gonna give alms to a formerly paralyzed man
Yeah.
Yeah, right your whole life's gonna have to change after that
Yeah, you're gonna be a hell of a healthy you're gonna have to go find work
You're gonna have to go right. Everything has to change after that
And there are a whole lot of people who either don't want to or scared to or just aren't ready to make the changes
They know they would need to make if that freedom came and so they don't want the freedom
They'll stay in their rut
at least for a while more. Right? So that is a very valid question when people
answer it honestly. Right? And that's because after the freedom, right? That's not like the end
of the story. It's like, okay, you're free. Happily ever after. Right? Now there's a lot of cleanup
that needs to happen. Now there's repentance. Now there's purification and healing of all the damage
that's been done.
sin and chaos and death and destruction in your life. And that takes work. We've talked
about repentance such as, oh, I'm sorry. Okay, not about my business. Right? That takes
a lot of work. Right? That takes a that takes a commitment. Right? And that repentance and
that work and that healing happen through the blood of Christ and the purification with
water.
Amen.
So, to wrap up, I wanted to talk, it's interesting, this is an episode about the Great
Blessing of Water, but I want to talk a little bit about the Eucharist, which we've already
talked about a bit, but I want to talk about another angle to this.
One thing a lot of people may not know about the Eucharist is celebrated in the Orthodox
church is that
the blood of Christ in the divine liturgy is made not just by the use of wine, but also by water.
So during the the
Prothesis or the Prochemydi is actually the name of the service
where the bread and the wine are prepared beforehand by the priest and the deacon if there is one.
One of the things that happens is
is that the priest
will place the liturgical spear in the side of the lamb, the piece of bread that is going to become
the Eucharist. And when he does that, he says, one of the soldiers pierced his side with a spear,
and at once there came out blood and water. And then he says, and then he saw his born witness
and his witness is true. This is obviously, quote, directly from the gospel of St. John.
And so after he does that piercing then
the deacon will take up water and wine and pour them together into the chalice.
So they come together.
Right? And so the connection between the language of blood and water and then of course of wine and water going into the chalice together is pretty clearly,
clearly made, you know, that these things are coming together.
And then also during the divine liturgy, right before holy communion.
hot water further is added to the chalice. And so there's water going into the
Eucharist as well on two different points, once during the preparation and
once after it's been consecrated and then hot water is added to it right
before the clergy commune and then of course the people as well. Again these
are all things that happen up in the holy place often out of sight of a lot of
people so they may not be.
aware that this is part of what's going on.
But there it is.
So this has always been done, I think,
the very earliest references to celebrating the divine
liturgy include the adding of water along with this.
And although this is not the great blessing of water
in terms of that particular service,
this is nonetheless water being used along with the wine,
or as we can also simply say water and the blood.
being used together, and it is for the same ultimately the same purpose,
although not in exactly the same way, but for the same purpose that the holy water blessed
and the great blessing of water is used. And that's this cleansing, this purification.
Right? We already talked about the line used when you combine the blood and the body together
for the pre-sanctified lamb.
but also like for instance in the traditional
post-communium prayers.
One of the prayers that's prayed,
now that there's all kinds of different services
for pre-communium, post-communium prayers.
So there's a bunch of them.
But one of the commonly prayed prayers
is called the prayer of St. Symmian,
the translator or Symmian metafrosti,
so it's a translator.
And I'm just gonna read a part of it for you,
but I think you're gonna hear in this
a lot of the same themes that we've talked about here
with blood and water.
Although who willingly just give thy flesh to me as food,
Guys, don't forget to subscribe.
And share this video.
Thank you.
Take care.
Bye.
fire consuming the unworthy consume me not oh my creator but rather pass through all my body parts
into all my joints my reins my heart burn thou the thorns of all my transgressions cleanse my soul
and hollow thou my thoughts make firm my knees and my bones likewise enlighten as one of my five
senses establish me holy in thy fear ever shelter me and guard me guard and keep me from every soul
corrupting deed and word chase and mere purify me and control me adorn me teach me and light me show
Don't need to be a tabernacle of thy-
spirit only and a no-wise the dwelling place of sin. That from me, the habitation, through
the entrance of that communion, every evil deed and every passion may flee as from fire.
And then it goes on a little bit after that invoking the saints. I mean, you can hear
in that exactly some of the same stuff we've talked about, right? There's a sense of cleansing,
hallowing, of purification from corruption, and then guarding and strengthening and returning
The human person back...
to the way that he's supposed to be. And this is said, consume me not, oh my creator. God
is invoked as the creator. And yet within this also you have the sense that I could be destroyed.
There's corruption. There's possible consumption. God is a fire consuming the unworthy.
So again, there's this ambivalent character in the Eucharist that it's fire and yet also
it's healing at the
same time, you know, that there's the possibility of being destroyed, but then there's the possibility
of being re-created, of being renewed. Right? And, you know, we've been talking now for
the past, what has it been two and a half months now? No, no, it's been almost trying to
think, if we're doing about two episodes, it has been months now. We've been doing this
episode of the sacraments, right? Like five months. Wow, the time just went by really fast.
And we discussed.
so many of these different holy services and what they do.
But I think one of the themes you probably have heard in all of them is this sense of
of purification which involves, of course, exorcism.
So driving out the darkness, but then also of renewal of recreation of
of making us to be as we were created to be.
Right? Because...
the world has come under the domination of darkness, of the evil one and over all of his
foul spirits. And I think that if we begin to see and then to act on an understanding of
the sacraments as experiences that if we participate in them rightly, rightously, repentantly,
will change us, will transform us and not adjust as a kind of, I don't know, sometimes
people experience this kind of like talisman, like I need to go get my communion.
I need to go get, you know, sometimes even, and I know people mean this innocently, but
sometimes they'll say, I need to take confession.
I'm like, you're not, you're not taking confession.
You're giving a confession.
Actually, you're making confession.
receiving absolution.
If we enter into these things knowing that what we're going in to do is to be purified,
to be renewed, to be exorcised, then I think that that will change our motivation from,
frankly, sometimes we have a sense of entitlement with regards to the sacraments, or maybe sometimes
we have a sense of obligation, so that's kind of the opposite of entitlement.
like, well, I have to be there, or just habit,
or even frankly, sometimes we can get bored
or be blase about them.
But if you remember what it is that they actually do,
what they're for, what their purpose is,
what they actually accomplish,
and not think of them as, you know,
these holy objects that you get,
or just something you have to sort of pass through,
you know, so that discounts or that counts, right?
If you experience it in this way, if you try to participate in this way, then it's going to be much more effective.
And we're going to become much more the holy people doing the works of God in this world and loving those around us as Christ loved us because he died for us even while we were sinners.
that it will be an experience of the sacraments that
an experience of power, of fire, of glory. It may not be something spectacular, right? Probably
not going to see sparkling lights or glowing whatever or whatever feels something. You may not
feel anything, but nonetheless, if you don't feel something, sometimes people do feel stuff,
and that's fine. But even if you don't, that it will have a much more profound and transformative
sense and and actually will be for your repentance.
actually will be for your transformation to become more like Christ.
And so I'm glad that we finished with this one on the great blessing of water because
it really has this very expansive sense of purifying, cleansing, renewing, resetting, recreating
us and the whole world all together.
Glory to God for this great, great gift.
Father Steven.
So, when I preach here in the parish, I'm actually always talking to myself out loud, in
that I try to find out what I need to hear, what I need to be confronted with, what I need
to be comforted by what I need to be directed toward.
And I just say that out loud.
to everybody. And at least a lot of the time I find that there are enough people like me that
it's meaningful for them too. They needed to hear it too. And so what I'm about to say is in
that spirit, right? As this year we're coming to the end of Lent tomorrow, technically.
and entering into the beginning.
of Holy Week. And as I try to think about the things that I and maybe some others who
might be listening need to repent of, there's one thing that in relation to what we've
been talking about in this episode, I think I need to focus on. And that has to do with
what we were talking about in the third half about no human person actually being evil
in it.
of themselves. Their I am a big fan of the whole locus of television programs, Breaking
Bad Better Call Saul, El Camino at all. And there was an interesting phenomenon that
happened while Breaking Bad was airing, which was that the main character, the central
character of that was Walter White. Who?
On all levels is really a despicable person and just how despicable he is is sort of revealed over the course of the show
He's responsible for deaths and murders and drug dealing and I write
everything
Full of pride full of resentment full of anger, right? I mean every he's just he's a slave to every passion in the book, right?
um
And interest
distinctly, the actress who played his wife, who within the context of the story was not
a flawless or perfect character had her own problems, but was largely the victim of her
husband and his choices. Nevertheless, received an incredible amount of hatred from viewers.
And this was sort of strange right on the face of it of like what's going on.
But sort of what was arrived at from the showrunner who created the show and other people thinking about was well here's the issue.
Walter White is despicable as his choices and everything he does on this show are right and he's a fictional character he doesn't exist.
But as wicked and evil as these things are, he's the protagonist of the show.
He's the main character. And so when another character, even if that other character might be
objectively more virtuous, when that other character stymies causes difficulties for
resists the main character, the audience is going to root for the main character against that
character regardless of their requisite virtue. Why am I bringing this up? I have a tendency and I
I think maybe some other people.
to sort of live our lives this way.
I am the protagonist of my life.
By virtue of just reality, I only see things from my own perspective naturally.
I have to work to try to figure out anybody else's.
So I fall into this protagonist slot.
And I tend very quickly to judge other people in my life based on those same criteria.
If I have things that I want...
that I like, that I desire, that I want to achieve, that I want to acquire.
And there's a person who stands in my way toward those things.
I judge that this is a bad person.
If there's a person who makes me feel good about myself and my choices and things,
I say this is a good person.
There's a person who makes me feel bad or questions my choices, questions my genius,
questions, you know, my accomplishments. This is a bad
person. This person made me feel bad. They are bad. And I judge everyone from my own perspective.
We pray over and over again in Lent and into Holy Week the prayer of St. Eiff from the Syrian
where we ask God to show me my own sins, help me to see my own sins and not to judge my brother.
This is what the idea of judgment is really all about.
It's not saying that you can't call sins in.
Any of that.
It's that I judge people based on their utility to me how they play into my own life and
end my own ego.
A person who's useful to me at a given point is valuable.
person who's of no really used to be an any given point in time is worthless.
as far as I judge from my throne.
This is a far cry from what we see presented in the scriptures.
This is a far cry from how God looks at people.
This is emblematic of the distance between me and God.
Because the person I encounter who makes me so angry
because he's so arrogant.
First of all, the only reason he makes me so angry.
is that I'm incredibly arrogant.
And it's easier for me to hate him than to hate my own arrogance.
But second of all,
is acting so arrogant because he's desperately insecure
and afraid.
And rather than me trying to get to know him
to understand that and to try and help him with that fear
and that anxiety and that insecurity,
I just judge him as bad, and I try to avoid him.
And I badmouth him.
Right.
The person who gets angry and stabs me, I say, well that's a bad person.
How dare they say that to me?
Right.
I don't know what they've been through that day.
I don't know what they're going through at home.
Frankly, I don't care.
I just care about what they said to me.
And how dare they.
And I, and maybe some of you who are listening,
need to reorient.
First of all, we need to reorient the story we think we're in.
If I'm the main character, I'm in the wrong story.
I need to be a supporting player, a tiny supporting role in the story of Christ in his church.
But secondly,
secondly,
what it means to honestly not judge your brother or sister,
means that regardless of
the encounter you have with them. Regardless of the feelings it triggers in you, regardless
of whether it helps you or hinders you toward some goal or some personal desire, that your
goal is to get to know and understand them and help them and love them.
Not just to be reconciled with them when the relationship is broken, but to develop a
a real relationship with them and understanding of them in the first.
life. This is a different way to live life. It's a much harder way to live life, but it's
a much better and more beautiful and peaceful and loving and joyful way to live life.
If we're willing to repent, if we're willing to be set free from our own egos and pride,
and were then willing to do the hard work of cleaning things up.
and moving in a better direction.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight, everyone.
Thank you very much for listening.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live,
we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsAdangeAndFate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page
or you can leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits.
And even if it's raining blood from a lacerated sky, you can join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, you can follow our page and you can join our discussion group. You can leave reviews and ratings everywhere also please, but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And awaiting the hour of a prize will your time slips away, so be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much. Good night.
God bless you. This is a shout out to Freedom Aviation and we pray that all of you would have a beautiful holy week and a blessed Palska.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De...
young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
Well, ancient faith radio presents readings from out of the grapevine with Dr. Chrissy
Hart.
Dr. Hart is an author and retired child psychologist living in York, Pennsylvania.